Inventory of the Petruška Šustrová papers, 1953-1997
Hoover Institution Archives
Petruška Šustrová papers, 1953-1997
2005C57
Šustrová, Petruška
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Photographs, correspondence, and related materials documenting the Czechoslovak dissident movement around Václav Havel in the 1970s and 1980s, the 1989 Velvet Revolution, and the role of the former dissidents in the post-communist government
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2005.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Stanislav Budín papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Czech subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Czechoslovak Independent Publications collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Tomáš Glanc collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Hana Konečná papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Josef Škvorecký papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
18 May 1947 Born
1966-1969 Studied Czech Literature and History at the Faculty of Arts, Charles University, Prague
December 1969 Arrested, sentenced on subversion charges, and imprisoned for the two following years
1971 Released from prison and consequently denied the right to finish her studies at Charles University
1971-1989 Officially employed at a post office, then later worked as a cleaner, or was officially unemployed
1972-1989 Involved in the samizdat publishing activities of the Střední Evropa journal, also as a member of the editorial board, and in similar projects
December 1976 Signed Charter 77 (Charta 77)
1985 Became Speaker of Charter 77
1979-Present Member, The Committee for the Defence of the Unjustly Persecuted (Výbor na obranu nespravedlivě stíhaných, or VONS)
1989 Rehabilitated on the charges of subversion from 1969
1989-1990 Journalist, Independent Press Center (Nezávislé informační středisko)
1990-1992 Journalist, the Respekt weekly
1990-1991 Advisor and later Deputy Minister, Czechoslovak Ministry of Interior
1992-present Freelance journalist (Lidové noviny and other periodicals), screenwriter (Czech Television documentaries on Georgia, Azerbaijan and Belarus) and translator (Paul Johnson's The Birth of the Modern, Norman Davies' The Isles: A History, and Anne Applebaum's Gulag: A History)
1999 Received the Karel Havlíček Borovský Prize for Journalism from the Czech Literary Fund
1999-2004 International Observer, elections in Georgia, Azerbaijan and Belarus
2004 Received the Officer's Merit Cross of the Republic of Poland (Krzyż Oficerski Orderu Zasługi Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej) from President Aleksander Kwaśniewski
Scope and Content of Collection
Photographs, correspondence, and related materials documenting the Czechoslovak dissident movement around Václav Havel in the 1970s and 1980s, the 1989 Velvet Revolution, and the role of the former dissidents in the post-Communist government.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Civil rights--Czechoslovakia.; Political prisoners--Czechoslovakia.; Dissenters--Czechoslovakia.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1970-1989; 1 (Box 1)
  Contains letters from the time of Šustrová's imprisonment (circa 1970), obituaries and other announcements or invitations. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Jitka Bodláková's (Šustrová's mother) letters to Šustrová, 1970 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Šustrová's letters to Jitka Bodláková, 1970-1971 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Jan Frolík's letters to Šustrová, 1970 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Felipe Serrano's letter to Šustrová, circa 1970 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Pavel Šremer's letter to Šustrová, 1970 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Martin Šustr's letters to Šustrová, 1970 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence: obituaries of Pavel Wonka (1988) and Jan Frolík (1972), Václav Havel's handwritten invitation to his 55th birthday party (undated) and other announcements and invitations, 1970-1989 (Folder 1: 7)
- Miscellany, 1989, 1991 and undated (Box 1: 8)
  Contains Šustrová's biographical note, leaflets, promotional materials and similar printed matter, including a xerox leaflet invitation for the commemmoration of Jan Opletal on 17 November 1989, entitled Vezmi si s sebou květinu (Take a flower with you; undated). Arranged generally in the original order.
- Photographs, 1953-1997 and undated (Box 1)
  Contains family photographs and photographs of Czechoslovak dissidents, including Václav Havel, during their informal and formal meetings, mostly in 1970s and 1980s, as well as photographs of the former dissidents as members of the official state administration during official events in the 1990s. Arranged chronologically following the original order.
  - 1958 and 1960s (Folder 1: 9)
    Contains the following three prints:
    Jiří Kabeš's wedding, 1953
    Petruška Šustrová with her brother, 1958
    Eva Olmerová, Polák (?) and Josef Škvorecký, Reduta Jazz Club, 1960s
  - 1970-1979 and probably 1970s (Folder 1: 10-11)
    Among the prints are:
    Jaroslav Hutka, probably 1970s
    "Jim" Čert, probably 1970s
    Zina Freundová and Karel Freund, probably 1970s
    V. Komrska and Jaroslav Šabata, probably 1970s
    Jitka Bodláková and Felipe Serrano, 1970 (?)
    Jan Frolík and Šustrová, 1973
    Petr Lutka, 1974
    Petr Kabeš and Pavel Šrut in a group photograph, 1974
    Jan Frolík, circa 1974
    Anna Šabatová, Petr Uhl and Šustrová, 1974-1979
    "Peták" Lampl, circa 1975
    Svatopluk Karásek, the Houska castle, 1976
    Vratislav Brabenec, Bojanovice, 1976
    Egon Bondy at a concert of The Plastic People of the Universe, circa 1976
    Wedding of Jaroslav Kukal and Šustrová, 1977
    Milan Hlavsa and Jan Schneider, 1977
    Jaroslav Unger, a member of Dr. Prostěradlo, a rock band, circa 1977
    Jana Převratská and Šustrová, 1977
    Miroslav Hrabaň, 1977
    Pavel Zajíček and other members of DG 307, a rock band, 1977-1979
    Ondřej Němec, Jaroslav Šabata and Šustrová, Hrádeček, 1978
    Pavel Landovský, Václav Havel and Jaroslav Kukal, 1978
    Svatopluk Karásek, Dana Němcová, Jaroslav Šabata, Dino Vopálka, Jiří Dienstbier and Šustrová, Hrádeček, 1978
    Jiří Kabeš, a member of The Plastic People of the Universe, 1978
    Pavel Landovský, Hrádeček, 1978
    Jiří Němec, 1978
    P. Kirschner and Jaroslav Kukal, 1978
    Přemysl Janýr, Petr Uhl and Šustrová, 1978
    Jan Brabec and Ivan Bierhanzl, 1978
    Josef Janíček, 1979
    Vlastimil Třešňák, Jan Brabec, Luděk Bednář, Jaroslav
    Kukal, Ivan Hrůša and Šustrová, 1979 (?)
  - 1980-1989 and probably 1980s (Folder 1: 12-13)
    Václav Havel in a group photograph, Hrádeček, 1980s
    Jan Placák and Šustrová, 1980s
    Vladimír Merta, 1980s
    Dáša Vokatá and Anastáz Opasek, late 1980s
    Vladimír Mlynář in a group photograph, late 1980s
    Jan Ruml in a costume of St. Nicolaus, probably 1980s
    Jan Šabata, probably 1980s
    Mlada Opočenská, Olga Havlová, Věra Jirousová and Šustrová, Hrádeček, 1980
    Martin Hybler, 1980 and 1984
    Olga Havlová, Luděk Bednář and Šustrová, 1981
    Ivan Martin "Magor" Jirous and Šustrová, Hrádeček, 1981
    Olga Havlová and Antonín Maněna, 1981
    J. Bělíková, Věra Jirousová, Květa Havlová, Jiří Němec and Šustrová, Hrádeček, 1981
    Aleš Havlíček, 1982
    Kamila Budovská, Gertruda Sekaninová and Šustrová, 1982
    Petr Cibulka, circa 1982
    Václav Malý and Šustrová, 1982
    Václav Havel and Ludvík Vaculík in Roman togas on a New Year's Eve, 1983
    Jan Placák and Šustrová, 1983
    Charlie Soukup, Vlastimil Třešňák and Šustrová in a group photograph, circa 1983
    Daniel Kroupa, Václav Benda, Pavel Bratinka and Šustrová, 1983
    Otka Bednářová and Šustrová, 1983
    ? Adámek being arrested, Brno, 1983
    Zdeněk Neubauer and Martin Palouš, 1984
    Jiří Křivánek in a costume on a New Year's Eve, 1984
    Jarmila Bělíková in a costume on a New Year's Eve, 1984
    Milan Hlavsa and Dana Němcová, 1984
    Lenka Procházková and Šustrová in costumes in a New Year's Eve group photograph entitled Rej domovníků (Dance of janitors), 1984
    Jiří Kantůrek, Andrej Stankovič and Šustrová in costumes on a New Year's Eve, 1984
    Jan Ruml, Václav Veselý, Václav Malý, Václav Benda, Martin Palouš, Pavla Paloušová, Zbyněk Hejda, Dana Němcová, Milan Hlavsa and Šustrová on photographs from a christening, 1984
    Andrej Stankovič and Petr Uhl in costumes on New Year's Eve, 1984 or 1985
    Vladimír Kroul, 1985
    Jiří Gruntorád, 1985 and undated
    Andrej Stankovič and Jana Veselá, 1986
    Pavel Tigrid, 1986
    Ivan Havel, circa 1988
    Rehearsals and recordings of Václav Havel's play Pokoušení (Temptation), 1988
    Ladislav Leština, 1988
    Luděk Bednář, 1988
    A human rights demonstration on Škroupovo náměstí (Škroupovo square), 10 December 1988
    František "Čuňas" Stárek, Vokno Publishing, and Šustrová, 1988
    Petr Placák, 1988
    Dana Němcová and Eugen Brikcius, 1989
    Meetings at the Bory prison, Plzeň (Pilsen), December 1989
  - 1990-1997 and undated (Folder 1: 14)
    Visit of Czechoslovak officials, including Šustrová, to Naples, Italy, 1990
    Ján Langoš and Šustrová in photographs from an official meeting, 1990
    F. Novotný, Ján Langoš, Jan Ruml, František Stárek and Šustrová, 1990
    Jiří Sirotek and Šustrová, Berlin, 1994